DAN KLEIN: Now we're going to talk
about model-free learning.
In model-free learning, we don't
construct a model of
the transition function.
What we do is we take actions.
And every time we take an action, we
compare what we thought was going to
happen to what actually did happen.
And whenever something is better or
worse than what we expected, we adjust
our values up and down.
So what we track in a model-free
approach is the values of interest
themselves, not the transition
functions or the rewards.
To get us started off, we're going
to think about the passive case.
So in passive reinforcement learning
the idea is things are happening in
the real world.
Some agent is taking actions and getting
specific outcomes that are
partially determined by chance.
You have to learn from these samples
you observe, but you
don't control the actions.
Someone else is choosing the actions.
And you're just sitting there with your
notebook trying to figure out,
based on the policy that is being
followed, what are the values of all
the states.
So you can think about this
here as this agent.
It's watching real things happen.
It can't rewind and try
something else.
But it's not in control,
it's just monitoring.
So the task we're going to think
about in the passive case is
this simplified task.
We're not going to try to figure
out how to act optimally.
We're going to try to figure out,
essentially, exactly what policy
evaluation did.
The input is a fixed policy.
And so, in code, you would receive a
policy and be asked to evaluate it.
In the sketch that I drew, the agent
is just watching some other agent
execute this policy.
But in any case, there's
a fixed policy.
The agent does not know the transitions
or the rewards.
This is still reinforcement learning.
Our goal is to learn the state values.
Now, of course, because we're watching
this policy, pi, execute, we're going
to learn the values under
the policy pi.
If pi is really bad, we're probably
going to learn values that are also
really bad, because they're the
values for this policy.
So this is policy evaluation.
We're watching or executing
a fixed policy.
And we're trying to figure out
how good each state is under
that policy's execution.
In this case, the learner
is along for the ride.
It doesn't get to actually control
things, even if it's already learned
they're bad.
We have no choice about the actions.
And we're just executing the policy.
It's still not offline planning.
We're actually taking actions
in the world.
We're just not being smart
about picking them.
The simplest way you could imagine doing
model-free learning is what's
called direct evaluation.
So remember, our goal is to compute the
values for each state in our MDP
under this policy, pi.
And the idea of direct evaluation
is super simple.
All we're going to do is
watch action unfold.
We're going to act according to pi.
And every time we visit a state, we're
going to write down what the sum of
discounted rewards, the utility,
turned out to be in the end.
And so, in acting, we will
have been in many states.
And for each one, we might have
been there many times.
We're just going to record what
happened, not in one step, but all the
way to the end.
When we average those samples together,
well, that'll be an average
achieved score for that state.
That's the value.
And if we do it long enough,
we'll got the right answer.
So this called direct evaluation.
Let's take a look.
We're given an input policy because,
remember, this is passive
reinforcement learning, and we're
only doing policy evaluation.
We're evaluating this policy.
So what do we do?
Well, we're going to get training
episodes again.
And we're going to execute
them one by one.
So maybe the first episode executes
and we see it happen.
These are the same episodes as before.
So let's think about this one.
In this one, we were in B.
We chose the action east.
We ended up in C.
We were in C. We chose
the action east.
We ended up in D.
And then we were in D. We
chose the action exit.
And we ended up in the terminal state.
The game ended.
We got our plus 10.
If we looked at just this episode, we
could say, all right, well, I've been
in B. I know something about B. What
utility did I receive from B?
It's not minus one.
That was the instantaneous
one-step reward.
According to this episode, from B
I received a total of plus 8.
So I might execute another episode.
This one turns out to be the same.
And again, from B, I received
a total of 8.
So I've got two examples now of,
according to this policy, I was in B.
And in the end, I received
a plus 8 total.
There might be some other episode.
So here's one where I go from E
to C to D. Again, I receive
plus 8 from the start.
But here, I receive that
plus 8 from E.
And then here's the weird episode
where I go from E to
C. I try to go east.
But when I execute the action east, I
actually end up in A, which turns out
to be minus 10, which, by the way, I
didn't know until I experienced that.
So what are we going to output?
Well, for each state we're going to
write down what we saw happen.
So for example, from B, we already saw,
we were in B twice, and each time
we received 8.
Great.
We've been in D a couple of times.
What's happened from D?
It's always been plus 10.
We've been in A once.
What's happened there?
Minus 10.
Now how about E?
We were in E twice.
Once we received plus 8.
And the other we received minus 12.
So what do we learn from all of that?
Well, we think 50-50,
plus 8, minus 12.
What do I get?
Minus 2, right?
All right.
Here's the interesting one.
What about C?
How many times have we been there?
We've been there four times.
And what have we experienced?
Well, we got 3 plus 9's
and 1 minus 11.
What's that?
It's plus 4 total.
Let's look at what we learned here.
Will this process work in the end?
Sure.
We're going to execute over and over
and over from every state.
We'll eventually learn that some of the
states are good and some of the
states are bad.
And eventually, they'll all be right
because, from each state, we will
eventually have a bunch of executions.
And the averages will
work out in the end.
But at least, for now, we've learned
something that's slightly insane.
Why is that?
What do we know about E
from our experience?
What happens when you follow
this policy from E?
You go to C every time.
All right.
What score do you get from E?
Minus 2.
What score do you get from C?
Plus 4.
Hm.
Something doesn't compute here, right?
How can E be bad, but the state
that it leads to every time
be reasonably good?
Similarly, B looks really good.
But it always leads to C, which
looks kind of mediocre.
So somehow, even though this is going to
work in the limit, we've thrown out
a huge amount of information about how
the states are connected together.
So what's good about this?
It's really easy to understand.
You just act.
And you take averages for
each state separately.
It will eventually work.
It satisfies our initial desire of
computing values without knowledge of
T or R. They're not optimal values.
They're values for the policy
being executed.
And it does the right
thing in the end.
What's bad about it is clearly
we're wasting information.
In particular, we're wasting information
about how the states
connect up to each other.
If we know that a state is good, and
we know that another state leads to
it, that state should be good as well.
And because we're learning each state
separately, were failing to exploit
information across episodes.
That means it's going to take
a long time to learn.
And we're going to have intermediate
results that are weird like this one.
All right.
So the key thing that's wrong with these
output values is that B and E
both go to the same state, yet somehow
they have different values.
Something's weird.
So you think we already
solved this problem.
We already have a way of exploiting
the fact that some state s is
connected in one step to
other state's s prime.
That's what policy evaluation
did in the first place.
And that's what the Bellman
equation said.
They said the value is determined by,
essentially, a one-step expect-a-max
connected to the other values.
Now in the case of a fixed policy,
the Bellman equation was
particularly simple.
And I draw these diagrams a lot.
We should make sure we understand
how to read these diagrams.
These diagrams are a representation
of the relevant
situation and Bellman equation.
When you're following some particular
policy pi, whenever you're at a state
s, you don't have a bunch
of actions to max over.
There's only one action, pi of s.
And that's shown here on the red line.
You then are in the q
state of s pi of s.
And something s prime
is going to happen.
Anything could happen.
And they're weighted by the
transition function.
And that's why you see here multiple
actions coming out.
So when I draw this, this represents
the case of the action being fixed,
but the outcome being
still up to chance.
And of course, if I can see all of those
different outcomes, I need to
transition function to know
how likely they are.
So the Bellman equations gave us this
policy evaluation where we started out
with depth-limited values.
We started out with v
of zero being zero.
And we computed the values under this
policy pi for increasing depths.
What was the equation?
Well, it's just that diagram
written down.
It says that, if you want to determine
the depth k plus 1 values for some
state, you say what will I
achieve from that state?
Well, whatever happens, I'll achieve 1
reward in the next time step and then
my future rewards, which are
discounted by gamma.
And I have to average over all
the outcomes according to
the transition function.
So what this is is it essentially says,
if you've got values for the
states, replace them with a
one-step-look-ahead, which in here is
just an average of real reward
plus future values.
And that gets us one step further
down into the tree.
And the rewards get incorporated
one step at a time.
And the overall estimates
become better.
So we'd like to do this, but we can't.
What's stopping us from running this in
the reinforcement learning setting?
It's beautiful.
It takes states, it connects
them up to other states.
It converges well.
We're missing something.
We're missing T, and we're missing
R. OK, so what do we have?
We've got an average.
Look at this thing.
It's complicated.
There's pi's everywhere.
There's a discount.
But in the end, it's an average.
It's an average of a bunch of things.
Each thing is a one-step reward plus
a discounted future from previous
computation.
And if we want to average a bunch of
things, we're back to that case of
having a model-based or
model-free option.
So this approach fully exploits
the connections.
But we can't do it.
And the key question is going to be,
how do we do this average without
knowing the weights?
And we already know how to take averages
without knowing the weights.
And that is we look at samples of
the things we're averaging.
And we add up those samples
with equal weight.
So let's think about how we can
turn that into an algorithm.